<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of my Lord Bishop of Worcester's letter touching Mr. Baxter from the animadversions of D. E.</title>
            <author>Yelverton, Henry, Sir, 1566-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13798649</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13798649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101891</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1055:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of my Lord Bishop of Worcester's letter touching Mr. Baxter from the animadversions of D. E.</title>
                  <author>Yelverton, Henry, Sir, 1566-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>D.E. is a pseudonym for Edward Bagshaw.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</term>
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</term>
               <term>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101891:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION Of my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s LETTER TOUCHING Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> from the Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>D. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> at the Anchor in the lower walk of the New-Exchange. Anno 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101891:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101891:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A VINDICATION</hi> Of my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter touching Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> from the Animadverſions of D. E.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>xpected, when I firſt ſaw theſe Animadverſions, that my Lord <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s Relation touching his carriage to Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> had been falſe in many particulars, and in all partial; for I could hardly believe any Ingenuous perſon could write ſo ſharply againſt a Father of our Church, if he did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he had truth on his ſide, as to the main occaſion of the Biſhop's Letter. But I confeſſe, I was much amazed, when I found our Animadvertor, not only ſilent as to the main buſineſſe, but of my Lord Biſhop's opinion as to the Controverſy, if Dr. <hi>Gunning,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Peerſon</hi> ſtate it right. And yet he is ſo angry, that through all this diſcourſe, he gives the Biſhop not one civil Epithete, never calls him Lord, but taxeth him of teſtineſs &amp; choler, of malicious &amp; ill-grounded fancy, of unpeaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; virulency, of trifling with Scripture, of boldneſſe &amp; impiety. And that this worthy Prelate might not go alone, he calls the Impoſers of Ceremonies unconſcionable, and ſo joyns all our Biſhops with him. I never yet, to deal
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101891:3"/>ingenuouſly, ſaw ſo much choler in ſo few words come from the pen of any perſon, much leſſe from one, whoſe judgement, as he tells us, is for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Biſhops, from one who ever oppoſed the Covenant, and is a zealous lover of the King.</p>
            <p>I am now more fully confirmed in my former opinion, that my Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Letter is unanſwerable, ſince our Animadvertor ſtrives rather to pick a quarrel with it, than to anſwer it. He had certainly a very great deſire of writing, or a very great animoſity againſt this Biſhop in publiſhing of his Animadverſions, ſince he knew before he writ them, that as to the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, the Biſhop was right, and only here and there takes out a paſſage, which he thinks may afford ſome diſpute. How well he hath done this, this enſuing Diſcourſe ſhall evidence.</p>
            <p>The firſt Exception he takes at the Biſhop is, that he ſuppoſeth ſo ſtrict an union, and inſeparable dependence between Kings and Biſhops, that they muſt ſtand and fall together. — I am glad he confeſſeth the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of this War is ſome advantage to this Poſition: But I believe if he looks but about him, he will hardly find any that oppoſed their Biſhop but did their Prince, as ſoon as they had power to do it. He means nor, I ſuppoſe, in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Axiom, the Anabaptiſtical or Fanatick party, the <hi>Munſter</hi> Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion will ſufficiently ſhew, their Principles, by their practices. And as for the Presbyterians, for them the World eſteems the moſt ſober of our diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, (although I am fully of Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgifts</hi> opinion, that they differ in nothing from them, but length of time, becauſe the conſequences of their Poſitions do naturally carry them to the Anabaptiſts) I wiſh I could ever find their Government in any place eſtabliſhed, but upon a War, but upon Arms againſt their lawful Magiſtrates. He that ſhould hear of <hi>Zuinglius</hi> killed fighting, of <hi>Beza</hi>'s trouping under the Banner of the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> of the <hi>Genevans</hi> expelling their Biſhop and lawfull Prince, of the <hi>Hugenots</hi> fighting in <hi>France</hi> againſt their lawful King, of the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſubverting their Monarchical Government into a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, of the <hi>Scots,</hi> to name no more, expelling their lawful Q. <hi>Mary;</hi> He that conſiders who firſt taught the lawfulneſs of taking Arms for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, invented the diſtinction of Offenſive and Defenſive Arms, and who generally teach the People, that the whole Power and Government is in them, will eaſily believe, that their Principles are inconſiſtent with Monarchy, which hath produced ſuch fatal effects throughout this part of the World. But this by the way; his firſt Reaſon why this Axiom is not true, is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Kings were in all parts of the World before Biſhops, and what hath been may be—I underſtand not at all how this is argumentative, becauſe there were Kings before there was any Chriſtian Church, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101891:3"/>ſo conſequently before Biſhops, therefore when there is a Chriſtian Church Kings can ſubſiſt without Biſhops: for whilſt the World was Heathen, we find a Monarchy amongſt their Prieſts, a ſuperiority and an inferiority evidently amongſt them, and ſo though there were not Biſhops, yet it was neceſſary to have ſomething that reſembled them. Amongſt the Jews we find three diſtinctions of Clergy, High-Prieſt, Prieſt, and Levites, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by God himſelf, which is a very probable Argument they were neceſſary to uphold a Monarchy, for they were neceſſary to uphold the Jewiſh Chuch, or elſe they had not been inſtituted. I could not have believed, that a perſon that ſeems Learned, could have thought that Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iom reached further, than ſince the World was Chriſtian. But if he only means, ſince the World was Chriſtian, why doth he not aſſign ſome Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy that ſubſiſted with Presbytery, I think he can name none but <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which how long it kept from a Rebellion, after Presbytery was by Law there eſtabliſhed, the Animadvertor knows as well as I do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe Biſhops as they are by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> are purely the King's ſubordinate Miniſters for the management of Eccleſiaſtical affairs. — This I think is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid than the former: for allowing what he ſaith to be true, which I am ſure is not, I do not underſtand, why becauſe the Biſhops are the Kings Officers, therefore there is not a neceſſity of Epiſcopacy in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, nay rather it inforceth the contrary, for it demonſtrates that Kings ever judged Epiſcopacy neceſſary to Monarchy by alwayes conſtituting ſuch Officers to Govern the Church under them. Our Animadvertor would do well to aſſign a King that put down Epiſcopacy, upon his own free will and conſent, without the force of the people, and ſettled up any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſtical Government, with which the Monarchy did better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. But beſides his Poſition is falſe: for the Law of <hi>England</hi> doth not look upon the Biſhops meetly as Eccleſiaſtical Officers, but as a third Eſtate, without whoſe conſent no Act of Parliament did legally paſs, unleſs they did voluntarily exclude themſelves; and that they are a third Eſtate ſeveral Acts of Parliament expreſſely call them ſo. Secondly, All Biſhops are to be conſidered in a double capacity: Firſt, As Officers inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo the Power of Church Cenſures belongs to them, and this Power our Kings never pretended to, to have, neither doth our Law any where cell you, that this Authority the King gives them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, As Officers appointed by the King to exerciſe that former power given them by God within ſuch bounds and limits. And many times out Law gives the Biſhop much power in the Secular affairs, which will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the good of the State as well as the Church; which Power they derive not from Chriſt, but from the Secular Magiſtrate. Now when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101891:4"/>the Magiſtrate is Chriſtian, it is neceſſary that the limits of each Biſhops Juriſdiction be determined by him, but were the Magiſtrate Heathen, the Church had that power to preſcribe the limits of each Biſhop, as we ſee they did in the firſt 300. years after Chriſt, and we find no Chriſtian all that time ever queſtion them. And the reaſon is evident, becauſe Chriſt that left the Biſhops the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, Governours of the Church, could not but give them ſufficient Power to do all things which was neceſſary to the peace, increaſe, and aedification of the Church, which certainly the appointing of limits for each Biſhop to act in muſt neceſſary conduce.</p>
            <p>But in the third place, I underſtand not how our Animadvertor agrees with himſelf, when he tells us the King may conferr the management of Eccleſiaſtical affairs upon Lay Men, &amp; calls the Epiſcopal power undue Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Praelation of his inferiour Officers, and yet ſome few lines before ſays his judgement is much for the Order of Biſhops. If he be for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Biſhops, he muſt believe they have a power from Chriſt which no earthly man can either give or take from them; but I believe he miſtook himſelf, or elſe he would not uſe ſuch uncharitable Epithetes of their whole Order, in calling it undue Dignity, and as ſome Antichriſtian. There is nothing more in theſe words but what before is anſwered.</p>
            <p>His third Reaſon againſt this Union is worſt ſtill. Becauſe it will be found none hath been greater Enemies to the undoubted Soveraignty of Princes than ſome Biſhops have been — Ergo Epiſcopacy and Monarchy are not neceſſarily united. I would in anſwer to this deſire our Animadvert or to name me any ſort of Men that are neceſſary to a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and let him examine himſelf whether this Argument is not againſt them. There are by Hiſtorians eſteemed two Foundations of Monarchy, Nobility or Arms: and have not many Noble-men, which ſhould be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Monarchies, been the ruin of them? Witneſſe the Barons Warrs, what neceſſities were ſeveral of our Kings brought into by them? And how often do we read in ſtory of Armies depoſing one Prince and ſetting up another? So that this Argument is as ſtrong againſt any ſort of Men, that a Monarchy makes uſe of, as againſt Biſhops. But now to uſe <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ad hominem,</hi> [for I confeſſe I cannot eſteem our Animadvertor a friend to Biſhops, though he ſayes he is, ſince he uſeth no civiler lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to one of them than to ſay the Pope is his Father.] Is that party that call the Dignity of Biſhops Antichriſtian leſs Enemies to Soveraign Power than ſome Biſhops have been? I believe whoſoever ſhall read the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Hiſtory of <hi>Scotland,</hi> written by Archbiſhop <hi>Spoſtwood,</hi> or ſhall but hear an impartial Relation of the Barbarous and unchriſtian uſage of our preſent King, when he was there, will be ſoon convinced, there never were a Generation of Clergy ſo Antimonarchical, as that Nation hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, amongſt the Presbyterian party.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101891:5"/>
I think now I have ſufficiently overthrown his Arguments againſt the Union of Monarchy and Epiſcopacy, It ſtill remains as firm as before. Yet I would not be miſtaken, 'tis poſſible a Monarchy may ſubſiſt without Epiſcopacy, for we may fancy all people ſo peaceable and juſt, as that a Nation may ſubſiſt without Laws. But that Axiom doth mean that Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy is neceſſary to the well-being of a Monarchy, not ſimply to the being of it, that the Church under a Monarchy can no wayes be prudently go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned but by Biſhops, nor the King can no way have that influence over the inferiour Clergy as by the Biſhops. I ſpeak here only in reference to the State. But as to the Church, Biſhops are an Order ſo neceſſary, that I doubt it will puzle our Animadvertor, or any perſon whatſoever to prove any Ordination but by their hands lawful in any caſe whatſoever.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Exception againſt this Reverend Prelate is, that he is the ſole Paſtor of all the Congregations in his Dioceſe — I could hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve our Animadvertor wanted Ingenuity before: For where doth my Lord <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſay, he is the ſole Paſtor of all the Congregations in his Dioceſe? The Biſhops words are theſe, For it is the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and not Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> that is Paſtor of <hi>Kederminſter,</hi> as well as of all other Parochial Churches in that Dioceſe. For there is much difference between my Lord Biſhop's ſaying, he is the Paſtor, and the ſole Paſtor: for the Biſhop is the Overſeer, and chief Paſtor, not only of all the Congregations, but of all the Paſtors in his Dioceſe, and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was not by any right preſent Paſtor there, and had no relation at all to that Parochial Church, as in his third Excep. I ſhall make appear. So that this angry confirmation of the Juſtice of his Exception falls to the ground. But let us follow him. If this be defenſible 'tis only by thoſe Arguments which are commonly alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to maintain the Popes Supremacy over all Churches whatſoever. For, ſince a Biſhop can no other way diſcharge his duty herein but by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding Subſtitutes, what hinders but that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> may overſee a Million of Churches as the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> 500? This illuſtration I think was purpoſely choſen to fling dirt in this Biſhops face, that the World might ſuppoſe Prelacy &amp; Popery go hand in hand, as their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant joyns them. But we muſt allow Ill words, from thoſe that write little Reaſon. This is grounded abſolutely upon a falſe Hypotheſis, for here it muſt be ſuppoſed that every Biſhops chief work is to feed his people, where his work is to govern, to ſee that the inferiour Clergy over his Dioceſe do their duty, &amp; teach therein ſound Doctrine. And this work as it is more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, ſo it is far more labourious. Neither is there the leaſt correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between 500. and a Million of Pariſhes, becauſe the account of the one may eaſily be done, the other is impoſſible. Beſides, 'tis quite a different thing the Popes claim and our Biſhops, for the Pope claims to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101891:5"/>Univerſal Biſhop, the only Succeſſor of the Apoſtles, and that Chriſt hath left him ſole Governour of the Church, and that all other Biſhops derive their power ſolely from him; whereas our Church teacheth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Opinion of the antient Fathers, as were it neceſſary I could ſhew you, that the Power of each Biſhop is alike, and as to their Precincts and Juriſdiction, the Governours of the Chuch under perſecution ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed more or fewer, according as the place required, and ever ſince, what alterations have been made in their limits, have been done by Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to whoſe care it belongs, as Governours of the Church, to ſee that each Biſhop performs his duty.</p>
            <p>But let us follow him to his Proofs, letting alone his unneceſſary paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis; his firſt is <hi>Act.</hi> 10.28. when <hi>Paul</hi> ſent for the Elders of the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he bids them feed the Church of God over which (not he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his ſole Authority as Biſhop of the Dioceſe, but) the Spirit of God had made them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Overſeers— I will not here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute what theſe Elders of the Church were, though St. <hi>Hierome</hi> tells me they were the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia,</hi> who I ſuppoſe might better know than any that lives in our age. I would here ask our Animadvertor, whether St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not conſtitute theſe ſeveral Elders over the ſeveral Churches, by laying hands on them, and appointing them to their work? I hope he doth not believe that the Spirit of God did in ſome viſible and extraordinary manner appoint theſe Overſeers, but that St. <hi>Paul</hi> being filled with the Spirit of God, did appoint them to ſuch a work. If ſo, what makes this to his purpoſe? and why ſhould not he believe that our Biſhops, though not in ſo extraordinary manner, are aſſiſted and directed by the Spirit of God to conſtitute inferiour Prieſts over the ſeveral Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, and to hinder thoſe that are erroneous, from infecting them? I am confident our Animadvertor doth believe, that the Miniſters of his party are aſſiſted by the Spirit in their preaching; why not our Biſhops in their governing? Now that this muſt be the meaning of the place, I think may very probably be educed out of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſummoning them to him to <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> in his charging them to perform their duty, &amp; in his freeing himſelf from the guilt of the blood of any of them, if they miſcarried, which he needed not have done, if he had not conſtituted them there.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His ſecond Proof is out of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> wherein he commands his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Elders to feed the Flock which was amongſt them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſfeeing them, acting like Biſhops, and not like the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> as lording over Gods Heritage, but as Patterns of the Flock. — So he. What is gathered from this? Ergo the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> is not chief Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of all the Pariſhes in his Dioceſe. I confeſſe, I am not quick ſighted
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101891:5"/>enough to ſee this conſequence, Nay, I think it is quite contrary, he bids them feed and overſee the Flock, therefore they were chief Paſtors of their Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſes: for if it be evidently clear, (as I think the Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> in his exquiſite Diſsertations hath made ſufficiently appear) that Biſhops were inſtituted by the Apoſtles, then there is no queſtion but that theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were the Biſhops he ſpeaks to. And this, were it now neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſhew, is further evinced, both becauſe the Apoſtle bids them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, two phraſes which are generally both in Scripture, and ancient Fathers uſed particularly to Biſhops in our ſence: Neither yet am I ſatisfied why <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth not ſignify lording over the Clergy, and I believe my Animadvertor can hardly render it better; but this is not now my buſineſs.</p>
            <p>But to go on, his Inference is as infirm as his Argument: for it doth not follow that becauſe a Biſhop and a Presbyter are names ſometimes given to one perſon, therefore as he would ſeem to intimate, that in the Scripture ſence they are one. But with his pardon, though he will find a Biſhop ſometimes called a Presbyter, as our Earls are called Lords, yet let him ſhew me a Presbyter called a Biſhop, either in Scripture or in antient Fathers. I am very confident he cannot, till then he hath done nothing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His third Exception is ſtill worſe, when he ſayes it ſeems to be a light, and to ſay no more, unſeemly trifling with Sacred Scripture, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm theſe words of our Saviour concerning ſuch as come not in by the Door, and therefore are Thieves and Robbers, ought to be underſtood of ſuch as Preach to Congregations without the Biſhops Licence. Thus he, And I deſire the Reader to judge, whether our Animadvertor deals ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. Where doth my Lord <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſay that he is a Thief and a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that Preacheth without the Biſhops Licence? His words are theſe, That Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was neither Parſon, Vicar, nor Curate of <hi>Kederminſter,</hi> or any where in my Dioceſſe: For he never came in by the Door, that is, by any legal, right, or Lawfull Admiſſion, but climed up ſome other way, namely by violence and intruſion, and therefore by Chriſts own inference is a Thief and a Robber, &amp;c. And I deſire our Animadvertor to tell me, whether he that by an unjuſt, and uſurped Authority comes into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans freehold, receives the profits thereof, and robs the Owner of his reputation there, is not more a Thief than he that Robs a Purſe on the High-way. I believe if <hi>D. E.</hi> had been put out of his Eſtate for his honeſty and loyalty, he would have counted the Poſſeſſors of it worſe than many that ſuffer publiquely for filching and ſtealing. But beſides, where doth the Biſhop ſay that he forbad Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to Preach, becauſe he did it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Licence, but becauſe he ſowed the ſeeds of Schiſm &amp; ſedition there? For which cauſe I thought in my duty (as being their Paſtor in Chief) not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101891:6"/>onely to forbid Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to Preach any more, which by the way he had done without my Licenſe; but, and theſe are my Lords words, now how ſtrangely doth he report what my Lord ſayes? He never ſayes he was a Thief and Robber, becauſe he came not in by his Licenſe, but becauſe he came in by violence and intruſion. But further, allowing the Biſhop did ſay ſo, which he doth not, Can he be ſaid to be come in at the Door, that comes in illegally? I can imagine but two wayes of coming in, either by the Door, or over the Pales, [<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.] which our Saviour men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and certainly if he that comes legally in, comes in by the Door, he that comes illegally in, comes over Pale, let our Animadvertor underſtand it either according to the Municipal Law of the Land, or the Law of the Church, which pleaſeth him beſt. But let us ſee his Arguments, why he that Preacheth without the Biſhops Licenſe doth come in by the Door. His firſt Argument is, becauſe then he knows not what Ordination ſignifies. — Yes, certainly you do know it gives him Authority to Preach, but not to another mans flock, nor in a Dioceſe where he hath no charge commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him. And this was my Lord's Reaſon, though he ſayes the principal reaſon was becauſe he Preached without his Licenſe, and very diſ-inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly leaves out the following words, having no cure of ſouls of his own to Preach to. Beſides, had he had a flock, my Animadvertor by the laſt words of his Arguments doth ſufficiently juſtifie the Biſhops proceeding, when he ſayes that moral and notoriouſly vitious miſdemeanors may be a ſufficient cauſe, and this certainly Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was guilty of, that Preached Sedition, Rebellion, and Schiſm, and that hath done what he could to make the King Odious to his people. His ſecond Reaſon is more ſtrange, for one Miniſter of the Goſpel (for certainly a Biſhop is no more) to ſilence another, and that for no better reaſon, but becauſe his fellow Miniſter is deſirous to Preach the Goſpel without a new Licence, is an abuſe of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. — I deſire the Reader firſt to mark his Parentheſis, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he that ſaid before, he was for the Order of Biſhops, now tells us that a Biſhop is no more than a ſingle Presbyter. Secondly, he is impartial in ſaying that the Biſhop did ſilence him, becauſe he did Preach without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, for this is one of the Biſhops Reaſons, he that reads the Letter will find many more. But thirdly, he contradicts himſelf, when he ſayes the ſilencing Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was an abuſe of Dominion, when he confeſſeth before, that for moral and notoriouſly vitious miſdemeanors he may do it. And whether M. <hi>Baxter</hi> be not much guilty, I am loath for his ſake further to enquire. But fourthly, and laſtly, allowing all he ſaith to be true, which I have proved falſe, that the Biſhop did abuſe his Dominion in ſilencing Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> doth this prove that what the Biſhop ſaith, that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> came not in by the Door, is a trifling with Scripture, when nothing is more
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101891:6"/>ſure, than that he that comes by violence into anothers profeſſion is a Thief and Robber by the Law of God and man? And this is all worth anſwering in his third Exception.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His fourth Exception is this. How conſiſtent with the Civil Peace (for I omit your Parentheſis, ſince it is nothing but railing) is the Biſhops diſtinction between the Act of Indempnity and Oblivion, when he tells us, that the King by it onely pardoned the Corporal puniſhment, but the Church had not, nor ought not to forgive the ſcandal, till honorable amends were made by Confeſſion and Recantation? — And now the Reader may perfectly underſtand what our Animadvertor is. I confeſſe, I ever found his party very unwilling to Recant their former miſcarriages, I wiſh to God many were not ready to Juſtifie what they have done. But till this day was ever there any Chriſtian thought, that the Church had not power over their Members to hinder them from any benefit by her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, unleſſe they gave ſatisfaction for their publique offence and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal? What was the reaſon the primitive Chriſtians underwent thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere penances, as the ancient Fathers, and ſeveral Councils mention, the firſt 300. years, if they believed not the Church had the power of Cenſuring? Nay, doth not his own party uſe them, where ever they have had any power? witneſs the frequent Excommunications in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> But I underſtand not what he means, by ſaying, the Biſhop makes the Church diſtinct from the State in coercive Juriſdiction. I know no coercive Juriſdiction the Church pretends to, for certainly to ſhut peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of her communion, is not a coercive power, to deny the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of her communion to notorious Sinners, till they recant and give ſatisfaction, the Church ever did, before the Magiſtrate was Chriſtian, and the <hi>Poenitentes,</hi> then, that ſtood at the Church porch bewailing their ſins, and begging the Churches prayers, did give ſatisfaction and recant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever there was the leaſt ſhew of coercive power in her. And therefore what this Reverend Prelate ſaith, is moſt true, that the King did but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the guilt or obligation to puniſhment, 'tis <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Deputies the Church muſt have ſatisfaction for the ſcandal and offence. And this is ſo little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Civil peace, that nothing can conduce more to it, to have men, ſenſible of their miſcarriages, recant and give publick ſatisfaction, will be our beſt means to prevent others from ſinning ſo again. I pray God the unwillingneſs of many to repent here, although the King hath pardoned them their corporal puniſhment, doth not oblige them to a worſe hereafter. And thus I have anſwered his fourth Exception. For as to the juſtifying this power in the Church, 'tis not my work, here to do it, and till the Anim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertor hath anſwered Dr. <hi>Hammonds</hi> Diſcourſe of the power of the Keys, that power he muſt as well as I believe in the Church, I have only ſhewed it very conſiſtent with the Civil peace.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101891:7"/>
5. His fiſt Exception is this. It is bold and impious when he affirms, that if to command an Act which by accident may prove an occaſion of ſin be ſinful, then God cannot command any thing— I underſtand not at all the Impiety in this Propoſition, for the Biſhop underſtands not this of Gods extraordinary commands, for God may by a new command diſpence with his own Law, as in commanding <hi>Abram</hi> to offer <hi>Iſaac,</hi> which had been murder had it not been done by Gods command, and <hi>Abram</hi>'s intention had been murderous and ſinful, but of his ordinary and common commands. Neither can it be any more Impiety to ſay, God cannot command any thing, than to ſay God cannot ſin, if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s poſition be true, and though God by his Almighty power may ſometimes and upon extraordinary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions diſpenſe with his own Law, yet it may be piouſly enough ſaid, God cannot command the breach of his own Law, becauſe it muſt be neceſſarily underſtood in his ordinary way of Diſpenſations.</p>
            <p n="6">6. His ſixth Animadverſion is. That in Divinity 'tis falſe and dangerous to affirm, That an offence unto which a diſproportionable penalty is annexed is not to be meaſured by the quality of the Act conſidered in it ſelf, but by the miſchievous conſequences of it. This he takes great exception againſt, but anſwers not the Biſhops Reaſons for it. But let us ſee what his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are againſt it. His firſt is, (to ſhorten his long Expreſſions) That for not ſubmitting to trivial Ceremonies, to debar one firſt from Chriſtian and then from Civil communion, is not juſtified by Scripture or Primitive Practice. This Argument firſt is particular, and that is no way argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative: for though all he ſhould ſay were true, yet it would amount to no more but to make one Exception againſt this Rule, and that would rather confirm than weaken it. 2. His Argument is perfectly begging the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, if he means that for ſuch forbearance they ought not to be forbid the Sacrament, becauſe the penalty is diſproportionable. But 3. did neither the Scripture nor Primitive practice juſtify it, yet if it did not condemn it, were there not the leaſt pretence in either for the practice of it, if it were totally ſilent in it, there is enough to perſwade the Church to do that which is for the benefit of the whole. But as his Reaſon is weak againſt this Poſition, ſo it is falſe in it ſelf: for it is much a leſs inconvenience to debar one from the Sacrament for not kneeling, than to break the peace of the Church by dividing from it, &amp; by infuſing into a multitude (which at all times is ready to embrace any novelty) principles of diſtruſting the commands of their lawful Paſtors; and if our Animadvertor did but look into the practice of the Primiviue Church, he would find ſcarce any offence was looked upon with a worſe Eye than Schiſm and ſeparation was, and that they were more
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101891:7"/>fatal to the Church, than the hotteſt Perſecution. I need not give Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for it, he knows enough already. As for the Texts of Scripture that are produced for it, ſince they are nothing more, but what every Nonconformiſt produceth for not conformity, and have been ſo ſufficiently anſwered by the Writers of our party, I omit to anſwer them, and the rather, becauſe the Reaſon againſt this Exception runs us in this Diſpute not the Poſition it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The ſeventh Animadverſion is, againſt that Chain of conſequences, which the Biſhop produceth. From diverſity grows diſlike, from diſlike En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, from Enmity Oppoſition, and from Oppoſition firſt Schiſm and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Church, and then Faction and Sedition in the State, and I would we had not found it ſo by our own experience, &amp;c. Theſe are my Lord Biſhops words, and this he calls a Rope of Sand, having firſt told us, that for proof of this, he virulently inſtances in our unhappy times. I ſhall not here tell our Animadvertor, that if he would have looked abroad, he might find other inſtances beſides this of <hi>England,</hi> but let us examine his reaſons, why this is a Rope of Sand. His firſt is, becauſe nothing is ſo clear, That there hath been, nay, ought to be Diverſities in external forms, without any diſlike at all as to the perſon of another. And his reaſon is, becauſe the Apoſtles that Preached to the Circumciſion, gave the right hand of fellowſhip unto the Apoſtles of the Gentiles, although their outward Rites in publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip were far more different than ours in <hi>Engl.</hi> In anſwer to this, I ſay firſt, That his inſtance of the Apoſtles is not at all the ſame, for though the Churches of the Circumciſion, and Churches of the Gentiles were often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in one and the ſame place, yet they were of different Communions, and this difference did ariſe not upon indifferent things, but upon things abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary. For the Churches of the Circumſion did follow Gods po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Command, which as yet they were not convinced were to be buried with Chriſt, ſo that the queſtion between them was not concerning the uſe of external Rites, but whether Gods Command, that injoyned them to the <hi>Jews,</hi> were ſtill in force or no? Secondly, I believe our Animadvertor himſelf doth not count Circumciſion an external Rite but ſomething more, ſince it was an Ordinance of Initiation into the Church of God, and was backed with ſo ſevere a penalty, that the Male that was not Circumciſed the eighth day, was to be cut off from the people. But thirdly, though the caſe be not the ſame, yet what animoſities and heart burnings did this difference cauſe amongſt the Chriſtians? was it not the cauſe of the Council held at <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem? Act.</hi> 15. did it not make St. <hi>Paul</hi> withſtand <hi>Peter</hi> to the face? 2 <hi>Gal.</hi> 11. and how many diviſions in after ages did this difference produce? as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly the keeping of <hi>Eaſter</hi> on the Jewiſh day of Paſſeover by the Eaſtern
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101891:8"/>Church, to name no more, ſo it appears evidently, the Church was never free from animoſities, till the Jewiſh Rites were quite laid aſide, and the whole Church became Chriſtian, that is, followed one and the ſame Rites. I ſay not this, I would not be miſtaken, that the whole Chuch univerſal, ought to follow one Rite, but I ſay, 'tis neceſſary to the peace of the Church, that every particular National Church follow one and the ſame Rites.</p>
            <p>His 2. Reaſon for his Animadverſion, is becauſe the State may be preſerved without the leaſt reference to the Church. And this I ſuppoſe he directs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulary againſt the laſt words of my L. Biſhops chain of conſequences, firſt Schiſm in the Church, then ſedition in the State. And truly no man can think this an ill inference, that conſiders the Doctrine of taking up Arms for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that conſiders this hath not been only generally taught, but by moſt of their party believed as a great truth. But his Argument herein is faulty to, for though the State did ſubſiſt without any reference to the Chriſtian Church, did it not produce moſt horrible Murthers, and blood ſheddings of the moſt loyalleſt of its Subjects? neither is the Reaſon good, becauſe a Heathen State was preſerved without reference to the Chriſtian Church, therefore a Chriſtian may without reference to a Chriſtian Church: for theſe States had ſtill a Church, though not of Gods, which their Laws and Conſtitutions had reference to, and without which 'twas impoſſible to have kept Government in that order. But laſtly, though 'tis poſſible a State may be preſerved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reference to the Church, can it prudently be done, and is it likely to hold long, ſince Religion hath upon many people a greater force than any Law. I am ſure, ſince the World was Chriſtian there was never ſuch an Example.</p>
            <p>His third Argument is, becauſe Unity doth not depend upon Uniformity, but upon Charity. And of this he gives no Reaſon, but his <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> unleſs giving the Biſhop ill words be a Reaſon. I hope our Animadvertor can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between Unity amongſt Individuals, and Unity with a whole body, for though the firſt conſiſts in Charity and candid forbearance, this latter can only viſibly conſiſt in Uniformity, and can only appear, in every perſon then joynly aſſembled uſing one and the ſame Rite. The heart, no man can ſee, and I believe let men never ſo well agree in their hearts, that only which makes this agreement viſible is their obſerving one and the ſame Rite openly. And ſo I have anſwered this Reaſon alſo, if it may be ſo called.</p>
            <p>To follow him, his eighth Animadverſion is. Whether as to the Matter of Fact, the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants do enjoyn ſtanding, and the <hi>Lutherans</hi> kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This he believes not upon the Biſhops ſaying ſo, but he hath more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe it than the contrary, ſince the practice of all thoſe places do teſtify it, for it is hardly poſſible to believe, that people are more willing to obey the Church, without Laws to back her, than with Laws, unto which a penalty is annexed. Our Animadvertor here falls from this matter of Fact,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101891:8"/>and diſputes concerning the <hi>Jure</hi> of preſcribing ſuch Laws. Now that is quite from the buſineſs here in hand, this Reverend Prelate urgeth it as a good Argument that our Church may enjoyn Rites and Ceremonies as well as the <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Lutheran,</hi> he ſhould ſhew Reaſons why our Church may not do it as well as others do, But he runs into another Diſpute, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which I will not follow him, ſince all this and ſtronger Objections are every where anſwered, by our Writers, who have undertaken to handle this Controverſy, as Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> the late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="9">9. His laſt Animadverſion is an accuſation of the Biſhop of Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe he ſayes <hi>Crimine ab uno — Diſce omnes,</hi> as if he did revile all the Presbyterian party, by reaſon of Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> I will repeat you the Biſhops words. You have before ſeen the Ingenuity and veracity, you now ſee the Humility and modeſty of the man, and in proportion of the whole party. Now this is but a taxing the Party but in proportion, and I would to God, what here is ſaid, was not too true. Beſides, this hath reference only to the humility and modeſty of the man, the other particularly belongs to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> as to the occaſion of the Biſhops Letter, and then are not all the party guilty, of counting it unlawful for our Church, to impoſe Rites, as others have done? and is it not a piece of arrogancy and immodeſty for inferiour Clergy to ſay this both of Church and State. But beſides, were this not allowable in the Biſhop, how comes our Animadvertor in the ſame breath to be guilty of the ſame Crime? and though he begins it with a Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical flouriſh, Would his Brethren the Biſhops take it well of a Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian to cry <hi>Crimine ab uno — Diſce omnes.</hi> See what manner of Spirits theſe Biſhops are of, and judge them all by the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s Example, yet we may ſee eaſily through it, and perceive the heighth of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe, when he prays God to deliver us from ſuch Biſhops.</p>
            <p>And I now have done with theſe Animadverſions, and I am glad, as <hi>D. E.</hi> is, that the World is not eaſily gulled with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then I am ſure what he hath ſaid will be to no mans prejudice but his own, Yet I muſt follow him in that which he calls a Taſt of the Biſhops wiſedom, and I am afraid the Reader will find little of that in the Animadvertor.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His firſt is, That the Biſhop ſaith, they did force all Communicants to be examined before they admitted them to the Sacrament—And this he calls a man of Straw for the Biſhop this weather to get him heat with, and why, becauſe, the cuſtom was to have one but once examined. Why doth the Biſhop ſay that a man was to be examined every time before he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? I find it not any where, and yet I have carefully read the Letter. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he is much out in thinking that Cathechizing and inſtructing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple before they received is all one with Examining, for the firſt puts the Receiver in a capacity to examin himſelf, the other like Auricular confeſſion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101891:9"/>diſcovers to the Prieſts, the thoughts of the Received hearts. But ſince our Animadvertor juſtifies not this, I ſhall ſay no more againſt it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I do not underſtand, why he ſhould be angry at the Biſhops ſpeaking againſt the Covenant, and not againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> for Preaching for it, ſince it was burnt. And with his Pardon this Reverend Prelate did with a Chriſtian Zeal, deſire thoſe books ſhould be burnt that were Printed in defence of it, ſince it continues deluded people in their Errors, and infuſeth in them that ungodly Principle of taking up Arms for Religion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But laſtly, I underſtand not why he is angry the Biſhop will write no more, when really, neither this Reverend Prelate, nor any elſe nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to have done it, unleſſe there were ſtronger exceptions brought againſt this Letter than are by our Animadvertor. And whether the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> will thank this Biſhop for ſighting, I am ſure the Presbyterians have little reaſon to do it, when their <hi>Goliahs</hi> do fall before him. But why the Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Age of this Prelate, his forein Travels, or rather baniſhment for a good a Conſcience, ſhould make our Animadvertor ſport, I know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, unleſſe it be the ſame, that induced him to make <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> his Patron, and to commend him in Print as his very good Lord.</p>
            <p>And now I have anſwered all but his railing, and that I ſhall onely do in our Saviours rule, in praying for them that curſe us, and deſpightfully uſe us. I have nothing more to ſay, but that though the Biſhop by other great affairs, had no leaſure to conſider ſuch Diſcourſes as this is, yet I that have more leiſure will promiſe him to anſwer what he ſayes, provided he keeps ſtrictly to the buſineſſe in hand, for if he runs out, to diſpute of the power of the Keys, of the lawful uſe of Indiffetent things, and ſuch like controverſies, I ſhall hardly find leiſure to follow him, and I am ſure there is already that ſaid for them which neither he nor his party can anſwer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101891:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
